<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss version='2.0' xmlns:atom='http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom'>
<channel>
<atom:link href='https://oli.me.uk/' rel='self' type='application/rss+xml'/>
<title>
(ollie {:on :parens})
</title>
<link>
https://oli.me.uk/
</link>
<description>
On languages and text editors.
</description>
<lastBuildDate>
Tue, 20 Feb 2018 23:28:45 +0000
</lastBuildDate>
<generator>
clj-rss
</generator>
<item>
<guid>
https://oli.me.uk/posts-output/2017-10-27-hello-world/
</guid>
<link>
https://oli.me.uk/posts-output/2017-10-27-hello-world/
</link>
<title>
Hello, World!
</title>
<description>
&lt;p&gt;I've, once again, migrated my blog onto another platform. This time I've gone from WordPress on my own Linode to &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Cryogen&lt;/a&gt; on GitHub pages. This means a few things:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;I no longer need to worry about running my own server, even though Linode is fantastic. I just don't want to maintain anything, especially WordPress.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I can blog with a Clojure based platform and integrate &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Klipse&lt;/a&gt; easily for interactive lispy posts.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;I can write my posts in markdown with Emacs and keep it all on &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Olical/olical.github.io&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the_migration&quot;&gt;The migration&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;I wanted to start fresh since my old blog is full of so many topics that I do not feel reflect my true interests anymore, so here I am with a blank slate. Luckily I found a way to keep my WordPress site exactly how it was so as not to break a single URL without running WordPress itself.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I used &lt;a href=&quot;https://en-gb.wordpress.org/plugins/simply-static/&quot;&gt;Simply Static&lt;/a&gt; to generate a snapshot of my entire blog which I could then merge into my GitHub pages repositories top level. This means every URL that used to work with my original blog will work with this one.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don't promote my old posts through this anymore, but they're still there, I even preserved &lt;a href=&quot;https://oli.me.uk/wp-index.html&quot;&gt;the original homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;the_payoff&quot;&gt;The payoff&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I think it was worth it since I no longer have to run a server and I can do things like this.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;klipse-scheme nohighlight&quot;&gt;(define (add a b)
  (if (= b 0)
    a
    (add (+ a 1) (- b 1))))
    
(add 10 20)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;p&gt;I also did this entire migration today while on trains and in cars over mobile internet, which was fun.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>
Fri, 27 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0100
</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
