<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Meta &#8211; Oliver Caldwell&#039;s blog</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/meta/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>On programming and text editing. Addicted to lisps.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Oct 2017 13:50:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-GB</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>hourly</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>1</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.8.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>My 2015 Bucket Set</title>
		<link>/2014/12/13/my-2015-bucket-set/</link>
		<comments>/2014/12/13/my-2015-bucket-set/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2014 12:00:58 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Oliver Caldwell]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Meta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[brainfuck]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clojure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clojurescript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[coursera]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[elixir]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[haskell]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[javascript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[khan]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=248</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I&#8217;m not really one for New Year&#8217;s resolutions, but this year I thought I&#8217;d create a sort of bucket list of programming related things to learn. But it&#8217;s more of a bucket set because the items are unique, I really want to focus on algorithms and data structures as well as a plethora of functional <a class="read-more" href="/2014/12/13/my-2015-bucket-set/">[&#8230;]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&#8217;m not really one for New Year&#8217;s resolutions, but this year I thought I&#8217;d create a sort of bucket list of programming related things to learn. But it&#8217;s more of a bucket set because the items are unique, I really want to focus on algorithms and data structures as well as a plethora of functional programming languages. So without further ado, here&#8217;s all the things I want to accomplish next year, this may grow considerably.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/">Khan Academy</a> algorithms as well as anything else I can fit in. Especially math and computer science related topics. I want to have something on the go at all times.</li>
<li>Algorithms <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partI">part I</a> and <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/algs4partII">part II</a> as well as <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/datavisualization">Data Visualisation</a> courses on <a href="https://www.coursera.org/">Coursera</a>. I&#8217;ve completed the <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/progfun">Functional Programming in Scala</a> course and completed most of Algo I, but this time I want to really ace it. I&#8217;ll have way more free time when I don&#8217;t have to commute for 2:30/3:00 hours a day.</li>
<li>More Vim plugins, I want to have five by the end of the year. So that&#8217;s three more on top of <a href="https://github.com/Wolfy87/vim-enmasse">vim-enmasse</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Wolfy87/vim-expand">vim-expand</a>. I have a few ideas lined up, but I can always rip good configuration out of my <a href="https://github.com/Wolfy87/dotfiles">dotfiles</a> and flesh it out.</li>
<li>A <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brainfuck">brainfuck</a> VM (idea courtesy of <a href="https://twitter.com/krisajenkins/status/543359911821053953">Kris Jenkins</a>, thanks Kris!).</li>
<li>A simple and useless language I am yet to design. I think it could end up being a project I can take as far as I want. Or drop it as soon as I get an MVP if I won&#8217;t learn any more.</li>
</ul>
<p>And the languages I&#8217;d like to learn and apply to this sort of thing are as follows.</p>
<ul>
<li>Clojure (I&#8217;m going to <a href="https://skillsmatter.com/conferences/6861-clojure-exchange-2015">ClojureX</a> at the end of 2015, so there&#8217;s an incentive!)</li>
<li>ClojureScript</li>
<li>Haskell</li>
<li>Elixir</li>
</ul>
<p>Other languages I may dip into if I feel like it.</p>
<ul>
<li>C</li>
<li>Java</li>
<li>Scala</li>
<li>Erlang</li>
<li>Ruby</li>
</ul>
<p>I&#8217;m pretty handy with JavaScript, but I&#8217;d like to build some stuff with <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> at some point too.</p>
<p>The projects and language lists may still grow, but I&#8217;d like to build and use these as a minimum. I&#8217;ll continue to blog about my endeavours and probably write a wrap up at the end of the year with a new set of goals for 2016. I think this goal based approach will help to accelerate my learning even more than my day to day work does. I may has skipped on university, but there&#8217;s no way I&#8217;m letting that leave a hole in my knowledge.</p>
<h2>In closing</h2>
<p>What&#8217;s better than a brainfuck VM?</p>
<p>A whole repository of them in different languages and styles. I&#8217;m going to implement a VM in languages I&#8217;m trying to learn that runs a brainfuck &#8220;Hello, World!&#8221;. I think that&#8217;ll teach me a fair amount about each language. I think it&#8217;ll be pretty cool if I use brainfuck as my platform for learning over the next year, it also gives me an excuse to litter my posts with profanities. So expect to see them appearing over at <a href="https://github.com/Wolfy87/brainfucks">Wolfy87/brainfucks</a> in the near future.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/12/13/my-2015-bucket-set/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>I want to learn stuff and write about it over 2015</title>
		<link>/2014/12/10/i-want-to-learn-stuff-and-write-about-it-over-2015/</link>
		<comments>/2014/12/10/i-want-to-learn-stuff-and-write-about-it-over-2015/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2014 21:28:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Oliver Caldwell]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Meta]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[clojurescript]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[khan]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[react]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[vim]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=240</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[I mean, I&#8217;ve been doing that on and (mostly) off for a while now, but I really want to focus on things like Khan Academy (which I&#8217;m currently using to learn more about algorithms). So hopefully you&#8217;ll see more frequent, yet short, posts on things I&#8217;ve recently stumbled across. I&#8217;ll try and write a few <a class="read-more" href="/2014/12/10/i-want-to-learn-stuff-and-write-about-it-over-2015/">[&#8230;]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I mean, I&#8217;ve been doing that on and (mostly) off for a while now, but I really want to focus on things like <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/">Khan Academy</a> (which I&#8217;m currently using to learn more about algorithms). So hopefully you&#8217;ll see more frequent, yet short, posts on things I&#8217;ve recently stumbled across. I&#8217;ll try and write a few in batches and space them out evenly to make it a little less sporadic.</p>
<p>I&#8217;m also looking to write way more Vim plugins and experimental &#8220;Hello, World!&#8221;-ish applications with novel technologies such as <a href="http://facebook.github.io/react/">React</a> and <a href="https://github.com/clojure/clojurescript">ClojureScript</a>.</p>
<p>I know this is a tiny and nigh on pointless post, but I felt that I had to put my intentions in words to put more weight behind it. My motivation will be acquisition knowledge and hopefully sharing it. Now I&#8217;m going to work on my second ever Vim plugin and a couple of little posts.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/12/10/i-want-to-learn-stuff-and-write-about-it-over-2015/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
		<item>
		<title>Hello again, WordPress</title>
		<link>/2014/08/06/hello-again-wordpress/</link>
		<comments>/2014/08/06/hello-again-wordpress/#respond</comments>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2014 21:32:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Oliver Caldwell]]></dc:creator>
				<category><![CDATA[Meta]]></category>

		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=96</guid>
		<description><![CDATA[Once again I&#8217;m reworking my personal website and blog. This time I&#8217;m aiming to journal my progress through projects that I work on in my free time (such as Vim plugins) as well as the odd rant or tutorial post, as I have written in the past. I felt that trying to force myself to <a class="read-more" href="/2014/08/06/hello-again-wordpress/">[&#8230;]</a>]]></description>
				<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Once again I&#8217;m reworking my personal website and blog. This time I&#8217;m aiming to journal my progress through projects that I work on in my free time (such as <a title="Vim EnMasse" href="https://github.com/Wolfy87/vim-enmasse">Vim plugins</a>) as well as the odd rant or tutorial post, as I have written in the past. I felt that trying to force myself to write large posts about huge topics and problems on a regular basis was just too difficult to keep up with in those precious few hours I have during some evenings. So my new goal is to journal my progress through my personal projects which should show other hows I work (sort of) and potentially teach other developers some neat tricks I didn&#8217;t realise were that neat.</p>
<p>I&#8217;ve decided to drop back to <a href="https://wordpress.org/">WordPress</a>, which I think is the third flip between a static (<a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>) and WordPress powered blog, which I am very happy with. <a title="Decode" href="http://scotthsmith.com/projects/decode/">The theme</a> is brilliant and amazingly configurable, <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/">CloudFlare</a> is optimising the hell out of it and I have a few plugins managing security enhancements and SEO tweaks on my behalf. Setting up the install through my host, <a href="http://webfaction.com/">WebFaction</a>, was painless and smooth, I couldn&#8217;t be happier really.</p>
<p>I hope to have many years of use out of my current set-up which will provide fresh insight and knowledge for as many developer as possible.</p>
<p>Here we go again&#8230;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
			<wfw:commentRss>/2014/08/06/hello-again-wordpress/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
		<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
